Julius Gold Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Julius Gold Collection1858-1924 (bulk 1920-1955)
ML31.G55
Gold, Julius, 1884-1969
circa 8,000 items 22 boxes 9 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Manuscripts of Gold's theoretical writings, including unpublished translations of and commentaries of the writings of Bernhard Ziehn. Also correspondence with colleagues and students, among the former Hans Joachim Moser, Lloyd Hibberd, and John Alden Carpenter, and the latter Winthrop Sargent, Frank Fragale, Meredith Willson, and Isaac Stern. Programs, printed music, finanancial and legal papers, and photographs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951--Correspondence.; Fragale, Frank, 1894-1955--Correspondence.; Gold, Julius, 1884-1969--Autographs.; Gold, Julius, 1884-1969.; Gold, Julius, 1884-1969.; Hibberd, Lloyd--Correspondence.; Moser, Hans Joachim, 1889-1967--Correspondence.; Sargeant, Winthrop, 1903-1986--Correspondence.; Stern, Isaac, 1920-2001--Correspondence.; Willson, Meredith, 1902-1984--Correspondence.; Ziehn, Bernhard, 1845-1912--Criticism and interpretation.; Ziehn, Bernhard, 1845-1912.
Subjects
Music theory.; Musicians--Autographs.; Musicians--Correspondence.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Jacob Zeitlein 1981.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Julius Gold Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1884 February 18 Born in St. Joseph, Missouri, of Russian-Polish parentage
1891 Family moves to San Francisco
1897 Studies violin with Sir Henry Heyman and Henry Holmes
1900-1905 Studies violin with Bernhard Listemann and Emile Sauret at the Chicago Musical College
1905-1910 Studies history and theory of music with Bernhard Ziehn
1910-1914 Professor of music at Drake University in Des Moines, Iowa
1914 Returns to San Francisco; plays violin with the San Francisco Symphony Orchestra until his resignation in 1937
1922 Plays violin with the San Francisco Opera Association until his resignation in 1937
1931 Summer Holds a lectureship at Stanford University: The Foundations of Music Art
1931-35 Professor of counterpoint and composition at Dominican College in San Rafael, California
1937- Private teaching and research
1969 January 29 Dies in California
Scope and Content Note
Julius Gold was a musicologist and teacher of both violin and music theory who was active in California in the first half of the 20th century. Having studied with the German theorist Bernhard Ziehn in Chicago from 1905-1910, Gold became an interpreter of Ziehn and one of his most avid apologists. Although his writings on Ziehn were never published, numerous typescripts of Gold's translations of and commentaries on Ziehn's writings are included in this collection. Gold also wrote extensively on the ecclesiastical modes, and the collection includes an abundance of writings and score examples both on modal doctrines and a wide variety of other subjects of music theory.
The papers of Julius Gold span the period from 1858 to 1964, with the bulk of the material covering the years 1920-1955. In addition to the writings described above there is extensive correspondence, both with notable colleagues such as Hans Joachim Moser, Lloyd Hibberd, and John Alden Carpenter, and with a great many of Gold's students, including Winthrop Sargeant, Frank Fragale, Meredith Willson, and Isaac Stern. Gold collected music books, amassing a 10,000 volume research library, and included here is a body of correspondence addressing the acquisition and sale of books and music, both by Julius Gold himself and by his daughter's firm, Glen Gold Books and Music. A large selection of publishers' catalogs is also pertinent to Gold's book collecting activities.
The remaining papers in the collection consist of promotion materials of Julius Gold and others, financial and legal papers, photographs, programs, and an assortment of printed music for the piano -- much of which may have belonged to Gold's wife, Janet Hale Gold, herself a pianist and a teacher of piano.
Organization of the Julius Gold Collection
The Julius Gold Collection is organized in 9 series:
Writings
Correspondence
Promotion
Programs
Clippings
Photographs
Financial / Legal Papers
Catalogs
Printed Music
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563509
Container List
- Writings (Box 1-5, Box OV 1-2)
  The Writings series is represented by two subseries: Writings of Julius Gold; Writings of Others. The materials consist of unpublished writings, translations and commentaries on German theorist Bernhard Ziehn. Gold also wrote extensively on the ecclesiastical modes, and the collection includes an abundance of writings and score examples both on modal doctrines and a wide variety of other subjects of music theory.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by subject or title.
  - Writings of Julius Gold (Box 1-4, Box OV 1-2)
    - General
      - Contrapuntal inventions: Tonal studies in a variety of moods and motives (Box 1)
      - The elements of musical composition (Box 1)
      - The Musico-Lexicographic Collections of Julius Gold (from brown 3-ring notebook) (Box 1)
      - Open sesame to musical knowledge (Box 1)
      - Proposals for a new dictionary of music (Box 1)
      - The tradition of patronage (Box 1)
    - Biographical and personal (Box 1)
    - Ecclesiastical modes
      - The beginnings of medieval modal theory (Box 1)
      - A brief bibliography of the history of modal doctrines (Box 1)
      - Modal bibliography (from blue 3-ring notebook) (Box 1)
      - Modal doctrines: A new perspective (Box 1)
      - The newer knowledge of the modes (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (typed and handwritten) (Box 1)
      - Score examples (Box OV 1)
    - Bernard Ziehn
      - Prospectus for editing The ecclesiastical modes by Bernard Ziehn (Box 2)
      - Ziehn's Harmonie und Modulationslehre: A commentary (Box 2)
      - Translation from Ziehn's Harmonie- und Modulationslehre (Box 2)
      - Translation of Ziehn's "Uber die Kirchentöne" (Box 2)
      - Notes on Ziehn (Box 2)
      - Score examples (Box OV 1)
    - Music theory
      - Canon (Box 2)
      - Chords and Triads (Box 2)
      - Enharmonics (Box 2)
      - Harmony (Box 2)
      - Instruments (Box 2)
      - Intervals (Box 2)
      - Modulation (Box 2)
      - Musical compositions by others (Box 2)
      - Polyphony (Box 2)
      - Scales (Box 2)
      - Symmetry (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (typewritten, handwritten, and 3x5 cards) (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (score examples; also 2 composition books containing handwritten notes on music theory and theoretical writings) (Box 4)
      - Score analysis (Chopin, Trois nocturnes, op. 9) (Box OV 2)
    - Proposals for teaching and study (Box 4)
    - Comments on writings by others
      - Essays in musical analysis by Donald Francis Tovey (Box 4)
      - "Das Lebenswerk Bernhard Ziehn" by Hugo Leichentritt (Box 4)
      - Review of unidentified work by Ziehn by [Edward] Mitchell (Box 4)
      - Letters to the editor, Contents: Life Magazine Musical Courier New York Times Saturday Review of Literature (Box 4)
  - Writings of Others (Box 5)
    - Grant, John [Fionn]
      - "The Celtic lyre.", Preface and list of examples only. (Box 5)
    - Ziehn, Bernhard
      - The church modes, Excerpts only.; Hibberd, Lloyd, translator (Box 5)
    - Isaacson, Charles D.
      - Face to face with great musicians. New York: D. Appleton & Co., 1929., Also published in London. (Box 5)
    - Leichentritt, Hugo
      - "Das Lebenswerk Bernhard Ziehns." (Box 5)
    - Mitchell, Edward R.
      - "Julius Gold and the teaching of music theory." (Box 5)
      - "Julius Gold: Master-musicologist." (Box 5)
    - Moser, Hans Joachim
      - Bernhard Ziehn., Chapters 1-3 (Box 5)
      - "Epochs of musical history.", Excerpt from Introduction. (Box 5)
      - Introduction to "Über die Kirchentöne" by Bernhard Ziehn. (Box 5)
      - Untitled article(s) for Musik in Geschichte und Gegenwart. (Box 5)
    - Offner, Herbert
      - The modal aspects of Bach's chorale harmonization, Master's thesis, University of California/Los Angeles, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Otterstrom, Thorwald
      - "The fugue," excerpt from Manual of harmony (advanced). (Box 5)
      - "Personal recollections of Bernhard Ziehn." (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous printed excerpts (Box 5)
- Correspondence (Box 6-14)
  The Correspondence series is represented by five subseries: General; Correspondence with students; Correspondence with family; Correspondence with institutions regarding jobs, grants, fellowships; Correspondence regarding acquiring and selling books and journals. The material consists of correspondence relating to the music, interests and pursuits of Julius Gold.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by correspondent or subject.
  - General (Box 6-9)
    - Adler, Clarence (Box 6)
    - Allen, James Turney (Box 6)
    - Allen, Warren (Box 6)
    - American Musicological Society (Box 6)
    - Apel, Willi (Box 6)
    - Bacon, Ernst (Box 6)
    - Barker, Orville W. (Box 6)
    - Barrymore, Lionel (Box 6)
    - Bates, A. Cyril (Box 6)
    - Berger, Isador (Box 6)
    - Blake, J. P. Art Publication Society (Box 6)
    - Blom, Eric (Box 6)
    - Blume, Friedrich (Box 6)
    - Boguslawski, Moissaye (Box 6)
    - Borowski, Felix (Box 6)
    - Bowhay, Arnold Beverly Hills Unified School District (Box 6)
    - Breeze, Louisa (Box 6)
    - Brother Leo (Box 6)
    - Brune, Adolf (Box 6)
    - Bukofzer, Manfred (Box 6)
    - Calvocoressi, M. D. (Box 6)
    - Cantor, Eddie (Box 6)
    - Carpenter, John Alden (Box 6)
    - Cesana, Otto (Box 6)
    - Chicago Symphony Orchestra (Box 6)
    - Chicago Tribune (Box 6)
    - Clark, William Andrews, Jr. Los Angeles Philharmonic (Box 6)
    - Colles, H. C. Grove's Dictionary (Box 6)
    - Cowper, Holmes See: University of California, Berkeley (Box 6)
    - Craft, Robert (Box 6)
    - Deutsch, Monroe See: Drake University (Box 6)
    - Downes, Olin (Box 6)
    - Drake University (Box 6)
    - Einstein, Alfred (Box 6)
    - Elko (Nevada) Independent (Box 6)
    - Elson, Louis C. (Box 6)
    - Engel, Carl (Box 6)
    - Engel, Gabriel (Box 6)
    - Foster Hall Collection (Box 7)
    - Freer, Eleanor Everest (Box 7)
    - Fulton, Muriel Mrs. Mario Palmieri (Box 7)
    - Ganz, Rudolph (Box 7)
    - Gehrkens, Karl W. (Box 7)
    - Goldberg, Albert Los Angeles Times music critic (Box 7)
    - Goldberg, Maurice (Box 7)
    - Godowsky, Leopold (Box 7)
    - Groshong, James W. (Box 7)
    - Guggenheim Foundation (Box 7)
    - Gunn, Glenn Dillard (Box 7)
    - Hartford, Huntington (Box 7)
    - Haydon, Glen (Box 7)
    - Heller, Helen R. (Box 7)
    - Hersholt, Jean (Box 7)
    - Hertz, Alfred (Box 7)
    - Heyman, Henry (Box 7)
    - Hibberd, Lloyd (Box 7)
    - Hill, William G. (Box 7)
    - Hinrichsen, Max (Box 7)
    - Hirsch, Paul (Box 7)
    - Hofmann, Josef (Box 7)
    - Holmes, Henry (Box 7)
    - Hughes, Dom Anselm (Box 7)
    - Irvine, Demar B. (Box 7)
    - Jeppesen, Knud (Box 7)
    - Jonás, Alberto (Box 7)
    - Journal of Music Theory (Box 7)
    - Kelley, Mrs. Edgar Stillman (Box 7)
    - Kleffman, Ervin H. (Box 7)
    - Krohn, Ernst C. (Box 7)
    - Kurth, Ernst (Box 7)
    - Lait, Jack (Box 8)
    - Lang, Paul Henry (Box 8)
    - Leach, Rowland (Box 8)
    - Leichentritt, Hugo (Box 8)
    - Liebling, Leonard (Box 8)
    - Lilienthal, T. and Jesse Lilienthal (Box 8)
    - Lowinsky, Edward E. (Box 8)
    - Luening, E. G. (Box 8)
    - Macmillan Company (Box 8)
    - Mason, Daniel Gregory (Box 8)
    - Mason, Redfern (Box 8)
    - Mathesius, Ebba (Box 8)
    - McEwen, John B. (Box 8)
    - Mendel, Arthur (Box 8)
    - Merton, Felice Mrs. Richard G. (Box 8)
    - Moore, Douglas (Box 8)
    - Monteux, Pierre (Box 8)
    - Morosco, Anthan (Box 8)
    - Moser, Hans Joachim (Box 8)
    - Music Library Association (Box 8)
    - Nettl, Paul (Box 8)
    - Olesen, Edith (Box 8)
    - Olson, Claire C. (Box 8)
    - Orriss, Herbert F. (Box 8)
    - Otterström, Thorwald (Box 8)
    - Parlow, Kathleen (Box 8)
    - Parsons, Louella O. (Box 8)
    - Paterson, John A. (Box 8)
    - Patterson, Frank (Box 8)
    - Persinger, Louis (Box 8)
    - Piston, Walter (Box 8)
    - Pratt, Waldo Selden (Box 8)
    - Purves-Smith, Claude (Box 8)
    - Reese, Gustav (Box 9)
    - Regnery, Henry (Box 9)
    - Remy, Alfred (Box 9)
    - Rowher, Jens (Box 9)
    - Rozsa, Miklos (Box 9)
    - Rubsamen, Walter (Box 9)
    - Russell, Rita and John Russell (Box 9)
    - Sachs, Curt (Box 9)
    - Sarton, George (Box 9)
    - Saunders, Richard (Box 9)
    - Scanlon, John Thomas (Box 9)
    - Schaeffer, Myron (Box 9)
    - Schmulian, S. E. (Box 9)
    - Scholes, Percy (Box 9)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, Includes: transcripts, correspondence regarding sale of Shaw letters (Box 9)
    - Silverman, Sol (Box 9)
    - Slonimsky, Nicolas (Box 9)
    - Sonneck, Oscar G. (Box 9)
    - Sorabji, Kaikhosru S. (Box 9)
    - Stock, Frederick A. (Box 9)
    - Swain, Arthur B. (Box 9)
    - Szigeti, Wanda (Box 9)
    - Teschan, Elsa H. Mrs. R. F. (Box 9)
    - Tobin, Richard M. (Box 9)
    - Torossian, Berdsch (Box 9)
    - University of California, Berkeley (Box 9)
    - Upton, George P. (Box 9)
    - Vincent, John (Box 9)
    - Wagner, Peter (Box 9)
    - Walter, Bruno (Box 9)
    - Weber, Julius Rehn (Box 9)
    - Werner, Eric (Box 9)
    - Who's Who in Music (Box 9)
    - Work Projects Administration (Box 9)
    - Zeisler, Fannie Bloomfield (Box 9)
    - Ziehn, Bernhard (Box 9)
    - Ziehn, Emma (Box 9)
    - Ziehn, Robert (Box 9)
    - Zubryn, Emil (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with students (Box 10-12)
    - Barthelson, Joyce (Box 10)
    - Campbell, Henry (Box 10)
    - Cesana, Bruno (Box 10)
    - Christensen, Dan (Box 10)
    - Coleman, Corinne (Box 10)
    - Copley, Frank (Box 10)
    - Edmunds, John (Box 10)
    - Ferguson, Allyn (Box 10)
    - Firestone, Nathan (Box 10)
    - Fragale, Frank (Box 10)
    - Frost, Robert (Box 10)
    - Garrett, Jack (Box 10)
    - Gillingham, Harry (Box 10)
    - Granat, Frank (Box 10)
    - Hayes, Jack (Box 10)
    - Herst, Jerome P. (Box 10)
    - Hurbert, Stanley (Box 10)
    - Kimbell, Ray (Box 11)
    - Kohanovich, Lydia (Box 11)
    - Larew, Walter (Box 11)
    - Mitchell, Edward R. (Box 11)
    - Ocnoff, Edward (Box 11)
    - St. Edmunds, John (Box 12)
    - Sargeant, Winthrop (Box 12)
    - Sharp, Florence (Box 12)
    - Sister Edmund (Box 12)
    - Sister M. Dominic (Box 12)
    - Stern, Isaac (Box 12)
    - West, James (Box 12)
    - Willson, Meredith (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (A-L, M-Z, Unidentified) (Box 12)
  - Correspondence with family (Box 13)
    - Gold, Glen daughter (Box 13)
    - Gold, Leon cousin (Box 13)
    - Gold, Jacob uncle (Box 13)
    - Gold, Janet Hale wife (Box 13)
    - Gold, Nathan cousin (Box 13)
    - Ross, Anabel Mrs. William D.; sister-in-law (Box 13)
    - Weil, Jennifer Mrs. Paul; cousin (Box 13)
    - Unidentified (Box 13)
  - Correspondence with institutions regarding jobs, grants, fellowships (Box 13)
    - American Operatic Laboratory, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Beverly Hills Unified School District (Box 13)
    - California Council for Adult Education (Box 13)
    - California Institute of Technology (Box 13)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York (Box 13)
    - Carnegie Institution of Washington (Box 13)
    - Cecil B. DeMille Productions Inc. (Box 13)
    - Drake University (Box 13)
    - Encyclopaedia Britannica (Box 13)
    - Federal Music Project (Box 13)
    - Fisk Teachers Agency (Box 13)
    - Ford Foundation (Box 13)
    - Guggenheim Foundation (Box 13)
    - Immaculate Heart College (Box 13)
    - Juilliard School of Music (Box 13)
    - Kansas City Conservatory of Music (Box 13)
    - Sol Lesser Productions, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Los Angeles City College (Box 13)
    - Los Angeles Conservatory of Music and Arts (Box 13)
    - Loyola University (Box 13)
    - Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Pictures (Box 13)
    - Mount Saint Mary's College (Box 13)
    - Musical Courier (Box 13)
    - Musical News (Box 13)
    - National Institute of Music and Arts (Box 13)
    - Paramount Pictures Corporation (Box 13)
    - George Pepperdine College (Box 13)
    - City of Philadelphia (Box 13)
    - St. John's College (Box 13)
    - San Francisco Chronicle (Box 13)
    - San Francisco State Teachers College (Box 13)
    - San Francisco Symphony Orchestra (Box 13)
    - San Jose State College (Box 13)
    - Stanford University (Box 13)
    - Universal-International Pictures (Box 13)
    - University of California, Los Angeles (Box 13)
    - University of Chicago (Box 13)
    - University of Colorado (Box 13)
    - University of San Francisco (Box 13)
    - University of Saskatchewan (Box 13)
    - University of Southern California (Box 13)
    - Warner Brothers Pictures, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Correspondence regarding acquiring and selling books and journals (Box 14)
    - Julius Gold (4 folders) (Box 14)
    - Glen Gold, Books & Music (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Tradition subscription requests (Box 14)
- Promotion (Box 14, Box OV 4)
  The Promotion series consists of printed fliers, brochures, placards, testimonials, etc.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by subject.
  - Julius Gold (including printed fliers, brochures, placards, testimonials, etc.), Contents: Plan of a representative school for music study and research T'jan, Bookseller and Importer Tradition: A magazine of musical inquiry (Box 14, Box OV 4)
  - Glen Gold, Books and Music (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous others (Box 14)
- Programs, 1960-1964 (Box 14)
  The Programs series consists of programs for musical performances (1900-1964, undated).
  Arrangement is chronological by date and alphabetical by institution.
  - Programs of musical performance (1900-1964, undated) (Box 14)
  - Programs of instruction (arranged alphabetically by institution) (Box 14)
- Clippings, 1860-1915 (Box 15, Box OV 3, Box OV 4-5)
  The Clippings series consists of periodicals, clippings, and promotional material about Julius Gold and various students.
  Arrangement is by format and alphabetical by title.
  - German periodicals
    - Allgemeine Deutsche Musik-Zeitung (Allgemeine Musik Zeitung), 1878-1914, See also: oversize box OV 3 for 1860 issue (Box 15, Box OV 3)
    - Allgemeine Musikalische Zeitung, 1820, 1868, 1871-73, 1877-78, 1880-81 (Box 15)
    - Deutsche Tonkünstler Zeitung (1910) (Box 15)
    - Monatschrift für Gottesdienst und kirchliche Kunst, 1897-1898 (Box 15)
    - Die Musik, 1915 (Box 15)
    - Musikalisches Wochenblatt, 1896 (Box OV 4)
    - Musik Welt, 1881, undated (Box OV 4)
    - Neue Zeitschrift für Musik, 1887-1905 (Box 15)
    - Unidentified (Box 15, Box OV 3)
  - Scrapbook, Clippings and promotional material about Julius Gold and various students. (Box 15)
  - American periodicals (Box OV 4-5)
- Photographs (Box 16, Box OV 3)
  The Photographs series consists of prints of Julius Gold, his family, etc.
  - Julius Gold, alone and with others (Box 16, Box OV 3)
  - Glen Gold (daughter) and her house (Box 16)
  - Others (Box 16)
- Financial / Legal Papers, 1934-1953 (Box 16)
  The Financial / Legal Papers series consists of bills, receipts, and other legal documents.
  Arrangement is by genre.
  - Bills and receipts, Contents: Glen Gold Books Residences Storage Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Certificates, licenses, contracts (Box 16)
  - Insurance (Box 16)
  - Medical (correspondence, receipts) (Box 16)
  - Musician's Union (membership cards, pamphlets, correspondence) (Box 16)
  - Papers regarding sale of Gold's music library (Box 16)
  - Tax Forms, Contents: Federal (1934-1943, 1944-1953) City, County, State (1937-1943) (Box 16)
- Catalogs (Box 17)
  The Catalogs series consists of catalogs from various publishers and institutions.
  Arrangement is by genre and publisher.
  - Publishers
    - American Institute of Musicology (Box 17)
    - D. Appleton-Century Company (Box 17)
    - Athenaeum Cremonense (Box 17)
    - Bärenreiter-Verlag (Box 17)
    - C. H. Beck'sche Berlagsbuchhandlung (Box 17)
    - The Bookfellows (Box 17)
    - Books & Music (Box 17)
    - Breitkopf & Härtel (Box 17)
    - Bureau of Musical Research (Box 17)
    - Cambridge University Press (Box 17)
    - El Colegio de Mexico (Box 17)
    - Concordia Publishing House (Box 17)
    - J. G. Cotta-Verlag (Box 17)
    - Deutscher Musikliteratur Verlag (Box 17)
    - Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt (Box 17)
    - Oliver Ditson Company (Box 17)
    - Ernst Eulenburg (Box 17)
    - J. Fischer & Bro. (Box 17)
    - Helen Gentry (Box 17)
    - Gesellschaft für Musikforschung (Box 17)
    - Ginn and Company (Box 17)
    - Walter de Gruyter & Co. (Box 17)
    - Wilhelm Hansen (Box 17)
    - G. Henle Verlag (Box 17)
    - Max Hesses Verlag (Box 17)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company (Box 17)
    - Insel Verlag (Box 17)
    - Institut d'Estudis Catalans (Box 17)
    - Institute of Renaissance and Baroque Music (Box 17)
    - Wm. A. Kaun Music Company (Box 17)
    - Ernst Klett Verlag (Box 17)
    - Leo Liepmannssohn (Box 17)
    - McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc. (Box 17)
    - G. and C. Merriam Co. (Box 17)
    - Edition Merseburger (Box 17)
    - Munksgaard (Box 17)
    - Albert Nauck & Co. (Box 17)
    - Martinus Nijhoff (Box 17)
    - Henning Oppermann (Box 17)
    - Oxford University Press (Box 17)
    - Edition Peters (Box 17)
    - Random House (Box 17)
    - Reclam (Box 17)
    - C. G. Röder (Box 17)
    - William Edwin Rudge (Box 17)
    - St. Martin's Press, Inc. (Box 17)
    - B. Schott's Söhne (Box 17)
    - Schweizerische Musikforschende Gesellschaft (Box 17)
    - Smith College (Box 17)
    - Steeger Verlag (Box 17)
    - Edition Steingräber (Box 17)
    - Universal Edition (Box 17)
    - University of California Press (Box 17)
    - University of Chicago Press (Box 17)
    - Arno Volk Verlag (Box 17)
    - Joseph Williams Ltd. (Box 17)
    - Yale University Press (Box 17)
  - Exhibitors
    - Goodspeeds (Early English Engraved Portraits) (Box 17)
  - Libraries
    - Foster Hall (Box 17)
    - Library of Congress (Box 17)
- Printed Music (Box 17, Box OV 3)
  The Printed Music series consists of music by various composers.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by composer and title.
  - Everest, C.
    - The Sabbath, a work containing the most popular psalm and hymn tunes in general use. Philadelphia: Lee & Walker, 1873., Signed: Eleanor Warner Everest, 1887; Noted in pencil: Bernhard Ziehn notations, see pages 299, 317, 327.; Pages 223-384 have been cut out (Box OV 3)
  - Fragale, Frank
    - Sprightly flight. New York: Edition Musicus, 1943., Set of parts. (Box 17)
  - Godowsky, Leopold
    - Progressive series of music lessons for the use of conservatories, teachers and students. St. Louis, Missouri: Art Publication Society, 1913. (Box OV 3)
  - Middelschulte, Wilhelm
    - Passacaglia (D moll) für die orgel. Leipzig: C. F. W. Siegel, 1901., Dedicated to Bernhard Ziehn. (Box 17)